<!-- 

  install.xml            orb package documentation
                                                               Juergen Mueller
                                                               Max Neunhoeffer
                                                                  Felix Noeske

         Copyright (C) 2005-2008 by the authors

This is the chapter of the documentation describing the installation.

-->

<Chapter Label="install">
<Heading>Installation of the <Package>orb</Package>-Package</Heading>
<Index><Package>orb</Package></Index>

To install this  package just extract the package's  archive file to
the  GAP  <F>pkg</F>  directory.<P/>

By default the <Package>orb</Package> package is not automatically
loaded by &GAP; when it is installed. You must load the package with
<C>LoadPackage("orb");</C> before its functions become available.<P/>

As of version 3.0, the <Package>orb</Package> package has a &GAP; kernel
component which should be compiled. This component does not actually contain
new functionality but will improve the performance of AVL trees and hash
tables significantly since many core routines are implemented in the C
language at kernel level.<P/>

To compile the C part of the package do (in the <F>pkg</F> directory)

<Verb>
    cd orb
    ./configure
    make
</Verb>

If you installed the package in another <Q><F>pkg</F></Q> directory than
the standard <Q><F>pkg</F></Q> directory in your &GAP; 4 installation,
then you have to do two things. Firstly during compilation 
you have to use the option
<C>--with-gaproot=PATH</C> of the <F>configure</F> script
where <Q>PATH</Q> is a path to the main &GAP; root directory 
(if not given the
default <Q><F>../..</F></Q> is assumed). <P/>
Secondly you have to 
specify the path to the directory containing your
<Q><F>pkg</F></Q>
directory to &GAP;'s list of directories. This can be done by starting
&GAP; with the <Q><F>-l</F></Q> command line option followed by the name
of the directory and a semicolon. Then your directory is prepended to
the list of directories searched. Otherwise the package is not found by
&GAP;. Of course, you can add this option to your &GAP; startup script.
<P/>

If you installed &GAP; on several architectures, you must execute the
configure/make step for each of the architectures. You can either
do this immediately after
configuring and compiling &GAP; itself on this architecture, or alternatively (when
using version 4.5 of &GAP; or newer) set the environment variable
<C>CONFIGNAME</C> to the name of the configuration you used when
compiling &GAP; before running <C>./configure</C>. 
Note however that your compiler choice and flags
(environment variables <C>CC</C> and <C>CFLAGS</C>) need to be
chosen to match the setup of the original &GAP; compilation. For
example you have to specify 32-bit or 64-bit mode correctly!<P/>

<Section>
<Heading>Recompiling the documentation</Heading>

Recompiling the documentation is possible by the command <Q><F>gap
makedoc.g</F></Q>
in the <F>orb</F> directory. But this should not be necessary.

</Section>

<!-- ############################################################ -->

</Chapter>
